<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-06T19:01:11+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Synchronisation in Stochastic Oscillatory Networks</title><link href="/2018/06/01/Synchronisation-in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synchronisation in Stochastic Oscillatory Networks" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2018/06/01/Synchronisation%20in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/01/Synchronisation-in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract:
<em>Fænomenet synkronisering er blevet undersøgt ved hjælp af Kuramoto modellen samt med forskellige tilpasninger deraf. Denne model beskriver en stor population af koblede oscillatorer. Tilpasningerne som er undersøgt her inkluderer en bimodal frekvens fordeling, tilføjelse af hvid støj, kobling afhængig af beliggenhed og en uniform faseforskydning. Vi reproducerer analyser og udfører simulationer, hvor blandt andet Monte Carlo metoder er brugt. Ved hjælp af tid-frekvens analyse baseret på wavelets er vi i stand til at opdage partiel synkronisering.</em></p>

<p>Supervisor: <a href="https://imada.sdu.dk/u/debrabant/index_en.php">Kristian Debrabant</a> (University of Southern Denmark)</p>

<p>External supervisor: <a href="https://www.math.rug.nl/~holger/">Holger Waalkens</a> (University of Groningen)</p>

<p>Have a look at my thesis <a href="/assets/Liefting_Time-Frequency_Analysis_of_the_Kuramoto_Model.pdf">here</a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/Sync_in_Stochastic_AppendicesBandC/KuramotoSDE2732.m">Code from Appendix B</a> (Runs simulations for the different adaptations of the Kuramoto model. Uses Monte Carlo method for the noisy Kuramoto model.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Sync_in_Stochastic_AppendicesBandC/phaseplot.m">Code from Appendix C</a> (Makes phase plots.)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: Fænomenet synkronisering er blevet undersøgt ved hjælp af Kuramoto modellen samt med forskellige tilpasninger deraf. Denne model beskriver en stor population af koblede oscillatorer. Tilpasningerne som er undersøgt her inkluderer en bimodal frekvens fordeling, tilføjelse af hvid støj, kobling afhængig af beliggenhed og en uniform faseforskydning. Vi reproducerer analyser og udfører simulationer, hvor blandt andet Monte Carlo metoder er brugt. Ved hjælp af tid-frekvens analyse baseret på wavelets er vi i stand til at opdage partiel synkronisering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time Frequency Analysis of the Kuramoto Model</title><link href="/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis-of-the-Kuramoto-Model.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time Frequency Analysis of the Kuramoto Model" /><published>2016-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis%20of%20the-Kuramoto-Model</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis-of-the-Kuramoto-Model.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract:
<em>The phenomenon of synchronisation is studied by means of the Kuramoto model. This model describes a large population of coupled oscillators with natural frequencies taken from a narrow distribution. It is assumed that the coupling between the oscillators is mean-field and purely sinusoidal. We follow Kuramoto’s analysis to obtain a formula for the critical coupling. Then the properties of the Kuramoto model are studied with the aid of Poincaré maps. We then conclude with a time-frequency analysis of the order parameter. With the aid of this time-frequency analysis we were able to detect partial synchronisation.</em></p>

<p>Supervisor: <a href="https://www.math.rug.nl/~holger/">Holger Waalkens</a> (University of Groningen)</p>

<p>Have a look at my thesis <a href="/assets/Liefting_Time-Frequency_Analysis_of_the_Kuramoto_Model.pdf">here</a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/orderpM.cpp">Code from Appendix B.1</a> (Computes the trajectory of the order parameter of the Kuramoto model.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/calc_trajCOPY.c">Code from Appendix B.2</a> (Calculates the wavelet transform of a single trajectory of the 3D system.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/dat_2_ppm.cpp">Code from Appendix B.3</a> (Converts the data to images.)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: The phenomenon of synchronisation is studied by means of the Kuramoto model. This model describes a large population of coupled oscillators with natural frequencies taken from a narrow distribution. It is assumed that the coupling between the oscillators is mean-field and purely sinusoidal. We follow Kuramoto’s analysis to obtain a formula for the critical coupling. Then the properties of the Kuramoto model are studied with the aid of Poincaré maps. We then conclude with a time-frequency analysis of the order parameter. With the aid of this time-frequency analysis we were able to detect partial synchronisation.]]></summary></entry></feed>