<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-07T13:27:16+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Hvad har ildfluer at gøre med de rytmiske celler i dit hjerte?</title><link href="/2022/06/14/Hvad-har-ildfluer-at-g%C3%B8re-med-de-rytmiske-celler-i-dit-hjerte.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hvad har ildfluer at gøre med de rytmiske celler i dit hjerte?" /><published>2022-06-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2022/06/14/Hvad%20har%20ildfluer%20at%20g%C3%B8re%20med%20de%20rytmiske%20celler%20i%20dit%20hjerte</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/14/Hvad-har-ildfluer-at-g%C3%B8re-med-de-rytmiske-celler-i-dit-hjerte.html"><![CDATA[<p>An outreach article for Videnskab.dk, find it <a href="https://videnskab.dk/naturvidenskab/hvad-har-ildfluer-at-goere-med-de-rytmiske-celler-i-dit-hjerte/">here</a> (in Danish).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An outreach article for Videnskab.dk, find it here (in Danish).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phase Reduction Based Feedback Design: Controlling Nonpairwise Interaction in Arbitrary Oscillatory Systems</title><link href="/2021/05/27/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interaction-in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Systems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phase Reduction Based Feedback Design: Controlling Nonpairwise Interaction in Arbitrary Oscillatory Systems" /><published>2021-05-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2021/05/27/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design:-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interaction%20in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/05/27/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interaction-in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Systems.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract: By designing feedback to control populations of oscillators, synchronisation in neurons causing epileptic seizures can be broken up. Oscillators (e.g. neurons) can be coupled on different levels. The most basic level is through links between pairs of oscillators. These pairwise links fail to explain phenomena such as peer pressure. The nonpairwise ‘links’ make such phenomena possible. Even though the effects of these nonpairwise interactions have been observed, described and modelled in a wide range of oscillatory systems, controlling nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems has remained a mainly unexplored area. We generalize synchronisation engineering to control nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems. As a first step, we design nonlinear time-delayed feedback that introduces bifurcations away from splay configuration into arbitrary systems. Controlling nonpairwise interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.</p>

<p>Session Abstract: Phase reduction is a powerful technique for the analysis and modelling of oscillatory dynamics in various applications, including power grids and biological systems, such as neural systems. A phase reduction describes the dynamics of weakly coupled limit-cycle oscillators in terms of their phase, a single variable for each oscillator. The effect of coupling between nodes in the network on the evolution of these phase variables is then captured by a single, phase response function, which can be inferred from data, or can be computed for given dynamical models. A barrier to the application of phase reduction approaches is that obtaining them is not straightforward, particularly when the oscillators cannot be isolated. Additionally, phase reductions are formally defined for weak coupling, that is, when the strength of coupling between units is small compared to the intrinsic oscillatory dynamics of each node. When the weak assumption does not hold, higher-order phase reduction techniques, or inclusion of additional dynamic variables, are often necessary to extend the validity of phase reduction. This minisymposium will highlight recent advances in the applicability of phase reduction techniques, covering extensions to phase-amplitude coordinates, efficient approaches for phase response function inference, and approaches for understanding and controlling higher order network interactions.</p>

<p>Talk at the SIAM Conference on Applications of Dynamical Systems 2021 (DS21).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: By designing feedback to control populations of oscillators, synchronisation in neurons causing epileptic seizures can be broken up. Oscillators (e.g. neurons) can be coupled on different levels. The most basic level is through links between pairs of oscillators. These pairwise links fail to explain phenomena such as peer pressure. The nonpairwise ‘links’ make such phenomena possible. Even though the effects of these nonpairwise interactions have been observed, described and modelled in a wide range of oscillatory systems, controlling nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems has remained a mainly unexplored area. We generalize synchronisation engineering to control nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems. As a first step, we design nonlinear time-delayed feedback that introduces bifurcations away from splay configuration into arbitrary systems. Controlling nonpairwise interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phase Reduction Based Feedback Design</title><link href="/2021/02/25/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phase Reduction Based Feedback Design" /><published>2021-02-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2021/02/25/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/02/25/Phase-Reduction-Based-Feedback-Design.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract: We will go through the concepts of oscillators, phase, isochrones, phase response curves and phase reduction. We then use phase reduction techniques to design weak nonlinear time-delayed feedback to control arbitrary oscillatory systems. The collective behaviour that we introduce to a system of oscillators in this way is described by a target phase model. In our generalisation of this (“synchronisation engineering”) approach, the target phase model can have nonpairwise interactions. Controlling nonpairwise interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: We will go through the concepts of oscillators, phase, isochrones, phase response curves and phase reduction. We then use phase reduction techniques to design weak nonlinear time-delayed feedback to control arbitrary oscillatory systems. The collective behaviour that we introduce to a system of oscillators in this way is described by a target phase model. In our generalisation of this (“synchronisation engineering”) approach, the target phase model can have nonpairwise interactions. Controlling nonpairwise interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Sync Engineering: Controlling Nonpairwise Interactions in Arbitrary Oscillatory Networks</title><link href="/2020/08/27/Beyond-Sync-Engineering-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interactions-in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Sync Engineering: Controlling Nonpairwise Interactions in Arbitrary Oscillatory Networks" /><published>2020-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2020/08/27/Beyond-Sync-Engineering:-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interactions%20in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/08/27/Beyond-Sync-Engineering-Controlling-Nonpairwise-Interactions-in-Arbitrary-Oscillatory-Networks.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract:
By designing feedback to control populations of oscillators, synchronisation in neurons
causing epileptic seizures can be broken up. Oscillators (e.g. neurons) can be coupled on different levels.
The most basic level is through links between pairs of oscillators. These pairwise links fail to explain
phenomena such as peer pressure. The nonpairwise ‘links’ make such phenomena possible. Even
though the effects of these nonpairwise interactions have been observed, described and modeled in a
wide range of oscillatory systems, controlling nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems has
remained a mainly unexplored area. We generalize synchronisation engineering to control nonpairwise
interactions in arbitrary systems. As a first step, we design nonlinear time- delayed feedback that
introduces bifurcations away from splay configuration into arbitrary systems. Controlling nonpairwise
interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.</p>

<p>You can find a video of this talk on Youtube <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OkpPhpxk_ls">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: By designing feedback to control populations of oscillators, synchronisation in neurons causing epileptic seizures can be broken up. Oscillators (e.g. neurons) can be coupled on different levels. The most basic level is through links between pairs of oscillators. These pairwise links fail to explain phenomena such as peer pressure. The nonpairwise ‘links’ make such phenomena possible. Even though the effects of these nonpairwise interactions have been observed, described and modeled in a wide range of oscillatory systems, controlling nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems has remained a mainly unexplored area. We generalize synchronisation engineering to control nonpairwise interactions in arbitrary systems. As a first step, we design nonlinear time- delayed feedback that introduces bifurcations away from splay configuration into arbitrary systems. Controlling nonpairwise interactions might advance the design of minimum-power stimuli for the treatment of epilepsy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Synchronisation Engineering Controlling Dynamics in Biological Oscillatory Systems</title><link href="/2020/06/19/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering-Controlling-Dynamics-in-Biological-Oscillatory-Systems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Synchronisation Engineering Controlling Dynamics in Biological Oscillatory Systems" /><published>2020-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2020/06/19/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering-Controlling-Dynamics%20in-Biological-Oscillatory-Systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/06/19/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering-Controlling-Dynamics-in-Biological-Oscillatory-Systems.html"><![CDATA[<p>Talk at the International Women in Engineering Day (<a href="http://www.inwed.org.uk/">INWED</a>) at the University of Exeter.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talk at the International Women in Engineering Day (INWED) at the University of Exeter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Synchronisation Engineering</title><link href="/2020/04/09/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Synchronisation Engineering" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2020/04/09/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/04/09/Beyond-Synchronisation-Engineering.html"><![CDATA[<p>Talk at the Dynamics Internal Seminar at the University of Exeter.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talk at the Dynamics Internal Seminar at the University of Exeter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kuramoto Model with added White Noise</title><link href="/2019/03/28/Kuramoto-Model-with-added-White-Noise.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kuramoto Model with added White Noise" /><published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2019/03/28/Kuramoto-Model%20with%20added-White-Noise</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/03/28/Kuramoto-Model-with-added-White-Noise.html"><![CDATA[<p>Talk at the Dynamics Internal Seminar at the University of Exeter. See Chapter 2 of my <a href="/2018/06/01/Synchronisation-in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks.html">master thesis</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talk at the Dynamics Internal Seminar at the University of Exeter. See Chapter 2 of my master thesis.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Synchronisation in Stochastic Oscillatory Networks</title><link href="/2018/06/01/Synchronisation-in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synchronisation in Stochastic Oscillatory Networks" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2018/06/01/Synchronisation%20in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2018/06/01/Synchronisation-in-Stochastic-Oscillatory-Networks.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract:
Fænomenet synkronisering er blevet undersøgt ved hjælp af Kuramoto modellen samt med forskellige tilpasninger deraf. Denne model beskriver en stor population af koblede oscillatorer. Tilpasningerne som er undersøgt her inkluderer en bimodal frekvens fordeling, tilføjelse af hvid støj, kobling afhængig af beliggenhed og en uniform faseforskydning. Vi reproducerer analyser og udfører simulationer, hvor blandt andet Monte Carlo metoder er brugt. Ved hjælp af tid-frekvens analyse baseret på wavelets er vi i stand til at opdage partiel synkronisering.</p>

<p>Supervisor: <a href="https://imada.sdu.dk/u/debrabant/index_en.php">Kristian Debrabant</a> (University of Southern Denmark)</p>

<p>External supervisor: <a href="https://www.math.rug.nl/~holger/">Holger Waalkens</a> (University of Groningen)</p>

<p>Have a look at my master thesis <a href="/assets/Liefting_Time-Frequency_Analysis_of_the_Kuramoto_Model.pdf">here</a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/Sync_in_Stochastic_AppendicesBandC/KuramotoSDE2732.m">Code from Appendix B</a> (Runs simulations for the different adaptations of the Kuramoto model. Uses Monte Carlo method for the noisy Kuramoto model.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Sync_in_Stochastic_AppendicesBandC/phaseplot.m">Code from Appendix C</a> (Makes phase plots.)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: Fænomenet synkronisering er blevet undersøgt ved hjælp af Kuramoto modellen samt med forskellige tilpasninger deraf. Denne model beskriver en stor population af koblede oscillatorer. Tilpasningerne som er undersøgt her inkluderer en bimodal frekvens fordeling, tilføjelse af hvid støj, kobling afhængig af beliggenhed og en uniform faseforskydning. Vi reproducerer analyser og udfører simulationer, hvor blandt andet Monte Carlo metoder er brugt. Ved hjælp af tid-frekvens analyse baseret på wavelets er vi i stand til at opdage partiel synkronisering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time Frequency Analysis of the Kuramoto Model</title><link href="/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis-of-the-Kuramoto-Model.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time Frequency Analysis of the Kuramoto Model" /><published>2016-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis%20of%20the-Kuramoto-Model</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2016/06/01/Time-Frequency-Analysis-of-the-Kuramoto-Model.html"><![CDATA[<p>Abstract:
The phenomenon of synchronisation is studied by means of the Kuramoto model. This model describes a large population of coupled oscillators with natural frequencies taken from a narrow distribution. It is assumed that the coupling between the oscillators is mean-field and purely sinusoidal. We follow Kuramoto’s analysis to obtain a formula for the critical coupling. Then the properties of the Kuramoto model are studied with the aid of Poincaré maps. We then conclude with a time-frequency analysis of the order parameter. With the aid of this time-frequency analysis we were able to detect partial synchronisation.</p>

<p>Supervisor: <a href="https://www.math.rug.nl/~holger/">Holger Waalkens</a> (University of Groningen)</p>

<p>Have a look at my thesis <a href="/assets/Liefting_Time-Frequency_Analysis_of_the_Kuramoto_Model.pdf">here</a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/orderpM.cpp">Code from Appendix B.1</a> (Computes the trajectory of the order parameter of the Kuramoto model.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/calc_trajCOPY.c">Code from Appendix B.2</a> (Calculates the wavelet transform of a single trajectory of the 3D system.)</p>

<p><a href="/assets/Time-Frequency_AppendixB/dat_2_ppm.cpp">Code from Appendix B.3</a> (Converts the data to images.)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: The phenomenon of synchronisation is studied by means of the Kuramoto model. This model describes a large population of coupled oscillators with natural frequencies taken from a narrow distribution. It is assumed that the coupling between the oscillators is mean-field and purely sinusoidal. We follow Kuramoto’s analysis to obtain a formula for the critical coupling. Then the properties of the Kuramoto model are studied with the aid of Poincaré maps. We then conclude with a time-frequency analysis of the order parameter. With the aid of this time-frequency analysis we were able to detect partial synchronisation.]]></summary></entry></feed>